Look at all the water now.
Isn't it crazy?
Morning of day 16.
The rain stopped
up in the middle
of the night somewhere.
And so we almost had
three full nights of rain.
-Ooh, Teal, look at this.
-Whoa.
That's crazy!
Here your blind's
completely underwater.
And I do believe your
fishing pole is as well, huh?
Yeah, the fishing pole
was tied off next to the blind,
so that's gone too.
Damn.
The environment's
changing quite significantly.
You know, all of the
animals were attracted
to our waterhole before,
so I had a blind set up there,
and that was a really
good hunting opportunity.
And now there's
water everywhere.
Yeah.
Seeing how absolutely
devastated this environment is,
it feels like it's never ending.
Ooh, look at this,
look at this tail.
Oh, gosh.
That's gotta be
like 15, 16 feet.
-Yeah.
-An absolute monster.
This is completely
unfishable now.
Yeah.
That's for sure.
The next stage
of the apocalypse.
-Yeah.
-Terrifying.
After two weeks
of intense heat...
Yes! I got it.
...and hard fought wins...
-It's dinner time!
-Yeah, buddy!
...heavy rains descended
on the wasteland...
...and pounded the
survivalists for days.
Holy!
It's been raining for
almost 24 hours now.
Oh, my God.
All we can do is pray
that we make it till morning.
Ah,
Without a roof on their boma,
Steve and Alexa and
Frank were left exposed.
We're hunkered down.
There's nowhere we can go.
If we get out in the rain,
we'll get hypothermia,
so it can take us
out of this challenge.
This is really up.
I can suffer, but
I'm only human.
You all right over there, Lex?
You OK, honey?
-Mm-hmm.
-Sure?
Yeah.
What's up?
I know, I'm sorry.
Yeah.
Avoiding hypothermia for
three nights in a row now.
Honestly, I've put my body
through some pretty things,
and that's pretty
much gotta top it.
We love you.
We're a team.
And we'd be there for each other
to the very, very end.
Huddled with Alexa in the
truck in the pouring down rain
at night, freezing
because I didn't
build a better shelter.
I felt like it was my fault
that she was suffering,
I felt like it was my fault that
she was freezing to death,
and it just crushed me.
Doomsday in Africa.
It surely is.
In this apocalyptic wasteland
of a place, when you don't have
that little glimmer of hope,
it's really hard to know
how long you
have to hang on for.
And inevitably,
that's gonna take a toll
on people's mental health.
Africa has been rough
on us to say the least,
but we're motivated.
We got a lot to do.
We gotta build up
our shelter more.
That's going to be top
priority, but we are hungry.
Yep.
With the rain
also, it kind of kills
our hunting activities,
since there's so many places
for these animals
to drink, you know?
Yep.
I'm gonna make sure that
we have firewood for tonight.
I'm just gonna hunt catfish.
I've had a lot of
teammates and survivalists
throughout the years.
I don't know too many
of them that could take
these giant transitions
from hot to cold,
just the extremes
that Africa has to offer.
So I'm gonna do whatever I can
to make sure that we're
gonna get through this.
The last few days have
been rough, and I mean rough.
Alexa, she's definitely
struggling the most
and food's running low.
So it is crucial that
we find another source
of protein out here.
Back in Florida, I do
quite a bit of bow fishing.
These catfish,
in the dry season,
when everything dries up,
they burrow down in the
mud and they start spinning
and the slime from their
skin creates, like this sack,
which keeps them alive
through the dry season.
And then, when the rains
come, they kind of burst out of that
and swim back up into the water.
So I think our chances
of eating some catfish now
are better than ever.
Here we go, that's a big one.
They're quick.
But we're getting closer.
Holy crap.
See? That's what
I'm talking about!
Hunger makes a better hunter.
That's a big sigh
of relief right there.
Hey, guys, you
ready for breakfast?
-What?
-I got a catfish.
-Hell, yeah!
-Look at this guy!
How'd you get him?
Did you shoot him?
-I got him with a bow.
-Holy!
-Hell, yeah, brother!
-Good aim!
-Good job.
-Nice, dude.
I've been really concerned
about how we're gonna survive,
but I find myself surrounded
by two teammates
who are incredibly skilled
hunters and fishermen.
-So I'm grateful.
-Man, that looks good.
-Yeah, it does.
-Yeah.
This place took
away a lot of our joy
over the last couple of days,
and I'm glad it's
given us some back.
Yeah, nature, you
get that little blessing
that, like, resets everything.
Maybe it feels some pity.
Nature knows no pity.
All right, babe, get in there.
Get in there, yeah.
Good.
Love that.
My first taste of catfish
in Africa will always be
-it tastes like hope.
-Yeah, 100%
Hope tastes a lot better
when you can actually eat it.
Right?
-Yeah.
-You know?
Oh, Stee, I know this
is gonna burn you alive,
but the sun feels so good to me.
-I hate the sun.
-Oh!
Desperate for their
first significant meal...
You know you're hungry
when you're picking
through some animal's
crap to find something to eat.
...the nonstop rain
delivered a crushing blow
to Wes and Steve.
Oh, man!
But a strange discovery...
What in the hell?
...brought an unexpected bounty.
Yes!
It's unbelievable.
-We're rocking it.
-Yeah.
Our shelter smells
like full on meat.
All the flavors from the
bones, the rest of the meat.
-Our shelter... -absolutely bomb proof.
-Yeah.
Storm comes in, we stay dry.
Brilliant.
I feel great.
You know, I got energy again.
And processing on
denial is going really good.
I mean, really good.
I couldn't be happier right now.
I tell you what, with all
that water we got now,
I think the game's gonna
be really widespread.
I'm glad we have the
meat stores right now,
because I think
hunting would almost be
-a waste of time right now.
-Yeah.
For day 16, we've got
to process the last bit
of our meat, get it
hung up, get it smoked.
We're gonna have us
a nice little stew tonight.
It's gonna be unbelievable.
What the hell is that?
-Ugh! Disgusting.
-That's bad.
Good lord... Well, this
is not good right here.
Yeah, it's gotta go.
You know, maybe it
had something to do
with the animal's
death originally.
Maybe that's where
something settled in.
But that's one of those things
you don't take a chance on.
You get rid of it.
Wait till the hyenas
and the lions smell it.
As bad as it smells,
they'll smell it for miles.
Yeah.
We're pretty comfortable
with the distance it is.
I mean, who wants to
have to fight for meat
in our shelter when it's free
and available 75 yards away?
Oh, man.
Look who came to visit.
Here's the elephant again.
And...
here is me.
Here's me in my home.
Unable to hunt due to
an aggressive elephant...
...and three days
of unrelenting rain...
It just sucks,
it's just abysmal.
...Joe is feeling the
weight of the challenge.
My energy level
is just depleting.
There he goes, right there.
He's probably a good...
oh, I don't know.
30 yards away.
Elephants can reach
a maximum speed
of 25 miles per
hour and sustain it
for over 200 meters.
That's almost twice as
fast as the average human.
He's going to do some
more marking of his territory.
Keep on walking, buddy.
This tree is marked by
the elephant that stalks me.
This shows intention.
He's a lone bull.
Unpredictable.
He could do
unspeakable things to me.
When they wanna attack,
they beat you, they stomp you,
they whip you against trees,
and then they bury the body,
you know, out of respect
or some practice they have.
I mean, they move silently.
It's unbelievable how
quiet they move through this.
You won't even hear them
till they're right on top of you.
They're not above
taking a human out,
and I just don't wanna
be that statistic out here.
Look at these scratches. They go
all the way down here to
the base, to the very almost
probably about 12 feet up.
So I wanna build a ladder
so I have an escape route
from my tree, so I
know now I gotta get
at least that high up
in order to escape.
So we need one long piece here.
So I'm gonna go scavenge
materials from the ruins.
Nope.
Let's see what we got here.
Oh, look at this.
That's a big old telephone pole.
The fact that this has been
laying here for 60 years
and still retains
some of its shape,
that's pretty damn good.
I could make that
a ladder, real easy,
but here's your guide
wire for this thing.
That thing is
probably buried deep.
Once standing nine feet
tall, the telephone pole
was supported by a thick
cable guide wire buried deep
into the ground.
To execute his plan, Joe
must first remove several bolts
and a bracket in order
to separate the pole
from the cable,
and then attach footholds
made from scrap wood
and scavenged nails
before finally securing it
to the tree to form
his escape ladder.
Having all these assets
means you've got to figure out
ways around, kind of, the
industrial parts of things.
And we don't have all the
tools, so it's this big balance
between what you have,
what the materials are,
and what can you do with
your own mitts and wits.
How do we get you free here?
It would slide off much
easier if I got this one bolt off.
And this wrench is too big.
That might work, actually.
Thank God, this is an
old pole with square nuts,
which they don't
really make anymore,
because it makes for
a good hitting source,
a good hitting
platform for this wrench
to, uh, try and get
this thing loose.
It's like flintknapping,
doing this, you know?
It's, like, strategic strikes.
Finale.
All right.
God, I hope this
pole doesn't get
super thicker at the bottom.
Ugh.
Is this going to take all
day, working it down?
Damn you.
Oh, my gosh.
I think so, mate.
Yeah.
Yeah, we can
give anything a try.
Sound like a lion..
I'll tell you what, I'll
get this outside door.
Do you wanna get that one?
Ooh...
Something really not
good is going on right now.
Oh, man, right there.
Oh...
Good lord!
Holy!
Oh,
Oh, man.
-Good lord!
-Oh!
Holy!
Oh,
Oh!
He's gone.
Oh, yeah.
You good on leaving everything
shut down for a few minutes?
Let's just leave it closed up.
OK, yeah.
Yeah, I mean, we've
got a holy moment here.
I've got more than
100 days under my belt
on "Naked and Afraid."
As an experienced survivalist,
I haven't seen anything,
like really, absolutely
nothing like this.
This is really a wake up call.
Oh, yeah.
It's unbelievable.
What you got there?
I'm gonna get into
some target practice.
I was wondering if
you want to join me.
Yeah, sounds good.
It's been a couple of days
since I pulled the
trigger on anything.
That's a big 200
pound male right there.
After several close
hunting calls... Oh.
...the discovery
of a fallen kudu...
Oh, my gosh, it's still wiggly.
...brought hope to Teal and Waz.
Oh, look at that.
Getting that red
meat endorphin rush.
That's super tender.
But three days of
rain and moisture...
...laid ruin to their
meat preserves.
Didn't get enough
of the moisture out.
This one, I know, is bad.
Smell that aged beef smell.
We need to kill something.
OK, we're gonna
start from scratch.
It's back to hunting today,
but I have to take into account,
you know, I... first to admit,
not a great hunter,
not even a good hunter,
but I won't be deterred.
I'm just gonna keep
going, keep chipping away,
keep learning, keep
adjusting until I finally get
that food on the table.
All right, it's at 20 yards
to that elephant poo?
-15, 18.
-15? All right, -Watch how close I get. -OK.
-Where was I?
-Just above.
Second shot.
Same spot, right?
No, just goes to the same spot
they're like
magnetized that way.
I still think I'm hitting
an animal there, right?
Mm.
As a target archer, I've
been shooting archery
for a very long time.
I think I first started shooting
when I was eight years old,
but my experience with the bow
is limited to sport.
I have a good bit of experience
hunting, mostly small game
with the.22 and shotgun
for birds, but not with a bow.
Oh, one from one.
Look at that, like a pro.
-Close.
-That's only half inch off.
I still think that
counts as a kill shot.
Woo!
Great shooting, Tex.
So, what I do is I
aim, and I shoot.
OK.
That's what I've
been doing wrong.
I've watched Teal
take a few shots now,
and I'm extremely impressed.
To her credit, you know,
she's probably a better chance
than me at hitting something.
Well, you're starting hunter,
and I'm backup hunter.
-No!
-Yeah.
Just seems like the
common sense thing to do.
Let's do that.
I'll do rock, paper,
scissors for it.
No, you're starting.
I would hate to think that
anyone was relying on me
to hunt for a food source
because, you know,
it's been shown time and time
again that's not my strong suit.
But with Teal, having her be
able to use that bow and arrow
is giving us an opportunity
to restock that food supply.
Definitely gives me a
little bit more confidence,
should we find
ourselves in a place where
we're hunting
something any day soon?
Yeah.
When we came together
as a team, I really felt
comfortable relying on
Russell and Waz to hunt,
and I felt like maybe
that's not my place.
But food is the top priority.
We have to eat.
So it sounds like it
might be the right time
to try my hand at it.
And I think there's
a very good chance
I might be successful.
Yeah, now we just have
to find a place to shoot.
Come on, baby
My goal is to get this...
Get this pole free
of the guide wire,
take it over to my tree,
and then use it as a ladder
to get up there so I have an
escape route from the elephant.
So I'm gonna need something
to get to higher ground,
much, much higher ground.
Of course, I thought
it would just slide off.
Is this a fool's errand?
It's only gonna get harder.
This is a bit like
Sisyphus right now.
Can't go that way,
can't go this way.
What am I doing? What am I...
why am I wasting so much energy?
This is where I've gotta stop.
That's a lot of calories spent.
So, damn disappointed in myself.
I gotta remember the pendulum
swings both ways, man.
You get an adrenaline
rush, you got a nice low
to come back to,
when that's gone.
Starting to get
a little blackout.
That's what I'm feeling
right now, so I've got to start
using my head more,
thinking more critically
and more conservatively
about my energy.
It's the only way
I'm gonna make it.
Just keep them in like a flower.
-Yeah.
-All right.
We had a pretty
good lion scare today.
It was not fun.
Did it make me really
take a hard second look
at safety precautions?
Yes, it did.
And so we're gonna set
up a little alarm system.
So what we're doing is...
-That's plenty.
-Yeah.
Sure.
Well, I'll let you tie
your end on that,
and then we'll stretch it out.
-Like it?
-Yeah.
A lot of wind moving through.
You know, the
wind's swirling around.
A lot of things will smell
that meat as the wind circles.
And so tonight's
gonna be very telling
'cause they know
where it is now.
-Hey, Stee, can you hear that?
-I can hear it.
I think those rocks in
there are gonna help it
-not make noise with wind.
-Yeah.
All right.
That'll help us.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
Mm, meaning...
That's it.
I don't know if I'll get
much sleep tonight,
'cause I traded in
the rain for high winds,
and this shelter and high winds
don't sound too good.
Every time a breeze
rips through here,
it's a horrifying
metal crushing sound.
Like this place is
gonna collapse in on me.
Oh, my God, this has
been the worst night.
This wind is just wreaking
havoc on the shelter,
I'm trying to rework it
and make it so it doesn't
do that anymore, 'cause
that's a horrifying sound.
Metal falls and creaks, and
the door goes flying open,
and cold wind comes rushing in.
It's gonna be another
long night, man.
I need my sleep.
That was the one thing
that I was controlling well
that was giving me
energy throughout the day.
And if that goes, then...
so goes my mental health.
This apocalypse is
kicking my ass right now.
The catfish, seems like
their numbers have increased
because of the rain.
I'm gonna make this fish trap
and this is gonna actually
be unbelievably cool.
It's gonna resemble
a lobster trap.
I'm using the pallet
boards and the wire
that Steve brought
back from the farmhouse.
So, what I'm doing
is, I'm gonna make
kind of a barrel,
and in the front of it
is gonna be a funnel.
A catfish should feel very
comfortable swimming in there,
and then once it's
in, it can't get out.
Wes has designed a scavenged
fish trap that will be closed
and baited at one end.
On the other end, he'll
build a funnel of wires,
which will guide
fish into the trap,
where the sharp prongs will
prevent them from escaping.
I've never made a
fish trap like this, ever.
And so, I'm pretty
excited to give it a go.
I need more wire, so I
gotta see what I can find.
In this apocalyptic scene
that we're walking through,
you really have to be creative.
I think the opportunities
to ramp up the survival
and turn it into a thriving
event is really here
if you just look
around hard enough.
A half dozen pieces like this
and my trap will be
absolutely like no escape.
OK.
I'm trying to find that
low hanging fruit right now
and conserve my energy.
Yeah, I'm tired.
Yesterday, I just wanted
to finish that telephone pole
and get it done.
But, you know, it's
just proving to be
a much bigger setup
than I could imagine
with the tools that I have
and the energy that I have.
So switching gears, real
quick, I've got to get smarter.
I've got to get more tactical.
Well, I found quite
a few nails here.
Today, I think I'm gonna
create a perimeter alarm system
using some trip wire
and some of the metal
that I have acquired.
That would be
helpful in the event
the elephant comes through.
There's a ton of shell
casings around here.
If I drive a nail into it, I
can put some wire on it,
and then nails plus casing
strung together on a wire.
Seems like whoever was
here used this as a place
to fire off, do some
marksmanship.
Really, kind of
suits this entire
apocalyptic challenge.
Probably got about 20 casings.
It's a good place
to start, I think.
So we gotta make like a
wind chime on the wire,
combining the nail
with the bullet shells.
So they kind of look like this.
If I can put some wire on it.
You know, I've got
these things here.
If I can get these
things to cling together...
That's a good alarm system.
I'll hang them up
with some wire.
And when I set it
up, I'll feel a lot safer.
Feels good seeing that
sun peek through the clouds
for the first time
in... Heck, yeah.
...three days.
It's the first time I've
been warm in three days.
-Right?
-Amazing.
It's gonna harden the
ground up nice and quickly.
Oh, it is the morning of day 17,
and today's it's a good
day, it's not raining.
The sun is out.
And honestly, like, yeah,
I feel like a new me today.
Jeez, our watering
hole just keeps getting
bigger and bigger.
Now that we have
energy, we need to focus
on the goal at hand,
catfish, and some shading
for the roof of our shelter.
This is four times as big
as it was three days ago.
-Yeah.
-Anything in it?
Nope. No catfish.
Nothing.
They're not quite as
active as they were.
They must have
calmed down a little bit.
These catfish are
so bloody smart.
They're either
smart or they're full.
This hillside, I always see
guineas moving through this
every day.
I should probably
concentrate on snaring them.
Yeah.
What have we got here?
Hey, guys.
-What? -It looks like -a bed liner.
-What's that?
Maybe it got washed
out of the mud.
What?
Look, you can even kind of see
-where the floodwaters came in.
-Yeah.
We got something
else up here, too.
-Yeah, what's that?
-Huh?
Yeah, buddy, Is this a door?
That looks like part of a door
for a stock trailer
or something.
That's a roof right there.
Yeah.
This massive storm that
raged for three plus days
washed some more
stuff down the riverbed.
And in this wasteland
of nothingness,
there is no waterproof material.
So seeing a flat, non-porous
surface is a beautiful sight.
Will the shelter
frame hold that?
It's heavy, but there's enough
joists to disperse the weight.
-And this means waterproofness.
-Yeah.
After spending the last
three days soaking wet.
Bring it back.
Throw it on the roof.
All right.
Door's kind of heavy.
It must weigh like
150 pounds at least.
Oh, yeah.
You want it right here, right?
Yeah, I'm thinking this way.
OK.
These poles aren't
in the ground that far.
Gotcha... And they're not
gonna take any side to side.
Gotcha, so let's
remove the ribs first.
Yeah.
-Ready?
-Yep.
-You got it, Frank?
-Get the big post.
-The beams.
Right in the middle.
-Yep, that side.
-Right there.
Further.
-There?
-Yep.
There you go.
-Towards me, more.
-Oh, no.
-Oh, God.
-No.
That's what I was talking about.
Yeah, no.
-This is a...
-I don't know if...
I don't know if this is
gonna be strong enough.
Can we put another
beam in over there?
I don't know that
this is gonna hold it.
No, we gotta push
these back that way.
-Oh, my God.
-It's all falling apart.
All right, let's bring it down.
We've got to bring it down.
Holy crap.
Towards me more.
Oh, no!
Oh, God!
Oh, my God, yep.
Holy crap.
Now, that sucks.
That could have been
really bad right there.
That could have been really bad.
Well, maybe that was
just the good lord telling us
not to do that, so that
we didn't die in our sleep.
One wind gusts the right
way, literally, murder somebody.
I think wanting
to be dry for once
kind of enveloped
our rational thinking.
And that's when
you don't survive,
is when the rational
thinking goes out the door.
That almost went
very, very, very wrong.
Oh, it did go very wrong.
Like, but it could have
been so much worse.
Like, we have to be
really careful, guys.
-Yeah.
The posts weren't really
deep enough, and with the rain
softening the ground up,
they were able to move.
So, same structure
again, deeper holes.
Same structure
again, deeper holes,
and we're not putting
a 200 pound steel door
on top of it.
-Yeah.
-Trial and error.
I tell you what, we
learned real quick.
It's a catch 22 with
man made materials.
I'm thankful for the things
out here that were left,
but we also gotta
be super hypervigilant
on how we use them.
Blessing in disguise.
Scary blessing in disguise.
Today, we're gonna build
a elephant warning system.
All right, so I've got this
bundle of barbed wire.
I'm gonna string
it through trees
at about this high, and
then I'm gonna hang
the bullet shell casings
that are rigged with nails
so that they'll hang and dangle,
and then I've got some washers
that they'll cling against.
So it'll create an early
warning system if anything
gets within a perimeter.
So I'm essentially gonna have
a warning system, my boma,
and then my shelter.
So I'll have three lines
of defense here in case
that elephant decides
that it wants to get
a little bit more intimate.
Putting this perimeter wire
about 50 yards from my shelter.
That way, I'll have at least
some time to know that
they're breaching this perimeter.
That should give me
enough time to get outside,
get around, climb the tree.
Who knows?
In the calm of the night,
it'll sound like something.
Dunzo.
Hold on, hold on.
Give me a break.
Hmm.
I am not doing
that great right now.
Let's go to the
shade. That's the best.
Out there in the
heat of the day,
all the rising and standing
and rising and standing
and walking and sitting
in the sun, like it just, uh,
it hit me real quick.
You know, just got that
tunnel vision, things started
to go gray, lost balance.
So, you know, I just
gotta realize, like, hey,
moving at that time of
day, it's really not good
for my health.
I'm only halfway
through this thing,
and I don't wanna slip into
some kind of zombie-like state.
So food is my number
one priority now.
You know, even if a
predator does come,
if I'm totally exhausted,
wasted, and lightheaded, like,
what am I gonna do?
I'm gonna fall over.
OK.
All right.
That's the bottom
of the fish trap there,
sealed up tight.
And now I just gotta
work on this top part.
Our very first day
of recon, we're still using
the same materials for tools
and to make our lives better.
OK, this sucker's done.
A decent sized
catfish goes in this trap.
He will stay there
until I get him out.
Our bait's gonna
be that rotten yellow.
Yeah, that's the
piece I want right here.
Catfish love
nasty stuff like that.
Here we go.
That is a fish
basket right there.
Full on fish trap.
Hey, Stee, any bites at all?
Yep.
Do you like something like that?
Yeah.
You ain't seen our
friend the croc, have you?
-Perfect.
-All right.
What if I cut some brush?
Yeah.
All right, I'm with you.
Hopefully, we'll get some.
Oh, God.
Hey, see a snake's skin.
-Right there.
-Oh.
Oh, yeah.
Well, it had to be
yesterday, day before,
something like that,
when it happened.
Might have, but we got
so many gaps under here
and everything, it might
have been living here.
It may still be living here.
We've got to start
being a bit more vigilant,
'cause the snakes are out
now, so I don't want to stand
on one, especially
a black mamba.
If I get bit, I'll
be out of here
within 15 minutes in a grave,
and I don't want that happening.
One of the deadliest
and fastest snakes
in the world, the black
mamba, attacks by rising up
and lunging to deliver
multiple bites to its victim.
Its highly toxic
venom acts quickly,
inducing heart
attack and paralysis,
and without antivenom
treatment, could be deadly
in as little as 20 minutes.
Ooh.
That's great.
So I just got back from
collecting some firewood,
and Teal's up in the blind,
right now, sitting right here
in that little hide.
She has been up
there three or four hours.
She's able to find the
perfect opportunity,
pop up and drop
one of these things,
I'm gonna be so excited.
I'm just gonna sit here
and just nervously watch
that field and see if a
kudu or a nyala come in.
All right, so I'm up in
the blind the first time.
I know this is my moment
to be able to provide
a good meal for Waz and
I, but it's so much different
when you're stalking something
and you're
anticipating it to move,
and that type of animal
knowledge, I don't have,
but hopefully we get a
couple in looking to feed.
Hopefully it's nyala
because they are a little bit
less skittish, but if it's
kudu, that is what it is,
and we'll try to get those guys.
Just gonna do our best.
Oh, she's got lots of
animals walking up on her,
this is exciting.
There he is, walking across,
it's right under
her blind right now.
They're moving in closer.
That's how close she is,
probably 20... 25 yards.
Oh, this might be her best shot.
Come on, Teal.
Oh!
That's so annoying.
How frustrating.
Oh, man!
I just missed that shot, and
I had so much to shoot at.
I was like, very careful,
stalked it super slow.
I stood up, I thought there
were only like five out there.
I stood up and
there was like 15!
And that humongous
one just staring at me.
I picked the smallest one,
and I... I thought I
was on target, but man,
not only did I miss, but I
missed a massive amount.
I feel like I could have
hit any single one of them
and I did not.
I literally just
totally whiffed.
I'm still in disbelief.
I feel like...
How could I have missed that?
Ugh!
-Hey.
-Welcome home, Miss Teal.
Tell me about day one of
your hunting adventures.
-Hmm.
-That little last group at the end there?
-Yeah.
-Just too many one?
I think that's what it was.
And I shot at the smallest
one, but I was way under him.
OK.
Between getting up slowly
and firing at a moving target,
and nothing having
bullseye on it,
it has proven to be just
as difficult as I thought.
Tearing apart
that telephone pole
had some advantages of
finding some new materials,
and I'm hoping
I can turn this
into a fishing reel.
Right now, I'm dragging,
I'm dragging hard.
So my next course of action,
and my focus is going to be
acquiring food, so...
Here is our
proposed fishing line.
So what I gotta do is
scrape off all this plastic,
exposing the wire.
My priority is to figure out
how to use that watering hole
to get food right now.
Hunting is not...
not the method.
The rain pretty much
obliterated hunting.
Now that there's
water everywhere,
the watering hole
is just not a place
where animals are gathering.
So, I'm gonna try turning it
more into a way to catch fish.
I'm holding a ceramic insulator.
Came off the power line,
so this is an early way
for power lines to be
wrapped safely would give them
some distance so that they
weren't able to arc to metal.
So I'm just trying to use
this bolt to create a handle.
By running a large bolt
through the middle
of a ceramic insulator
and securing it
with two metal nuts,
Joe's makeshift reel will
allow him to more easily
spool and guide
his fishing line.
All right, now let's see if
we can find a good thorn.
Try and make a thorn hook.
Oh!
All right, we're just
going to get some...
hay.
See, I think that's when
I start cussing a lot.
That's when I start
to get lightheaded.
That's when all the
swearing just comes out.
Ugh... all right, so found
these sickle bush thorns.
And, you know, these things
have been creating havoc
on my feet this whole time.
I think it's time I use
them to my advantage.
Then I'll wire wrap it so
that the wire is the eyelet.
That should be good.
The hook is good.
Got a nice strong eyelet.
I mean, I've starved my way
through a challenge before,
and that's not what I want here.
Gotta use the elements
and the items around me
so that I can just
bring in more food.
Yeah, there we go.
All right, OK.
Last one.
-There we go.
-Boom.
-That works.
-...Following the shelter debacle,
we decided that
it's probably best
if we go back to
our original idea
of the canopy, which was
always meant to be designed
as a sunshade, while Frank
starts concentrating on food.
I figured, I'm just gonna
start setting guinea snares.
OK, yeah, cool.
-Perfect.
-Get after it.
-Good luck, buddy.
-Yeah.
Good luck, godspeed.
Um, I'll cut all the wires
out of that other cab.
Yep.
And then, while
you're tying these in,
-I'll start chopping green stuff.
-Yep.
-Wires.
-Awesome.
I'm using wires that I've
pulled out of some cars
and securing the
corners of the poles.
And Steven is cutting
down all the green foliage
that is gonna on top.
Hopefully, that's gonna
mean that the structure is
far more secure, so when
we start throwing things on top,
it's not gonna move.
Through there.
Boom. There you go.
-Boom.
-OK.
So now what we're gonna
do is literally just toss it on top.
There you go. Boom.
-Perfect.
-Awesome.
Looks pretty cool, hey?
I love it, 'cause it's like
mixing of two worlds.
-Yeah.
-Right? You've got
the primitive survival,
and then you've got
-urban survival.
-Yeah.
Nice!
This area here, I think,
is a really good spot.
I always see guineas
moving through this.
The style of snare I'm gonna
do, it's a spring pole snare,
but it's actually called
an African bird snare.
Pretty much
invented for guineas.
A spring pole snare uses a noose
tied to a bent
sapling for tension.
It's then tied to
a trigger stick,
that is anchored
under an exposed root
and propped up
with a bait stick.
When the guinea fowl
disturbs the bait stick,
it triggers the trap,
tightening the noose
around the bird.
There's my loop.
It's all woven in there.
So I made these snares
with my Pawnee bark,
and I'm gonna scratch the
ground out as I make this
to make it look like something's
been in there digging.
And that usually drives
scratching birds nuts.
It makes them think
that somebody's getting
something that they're not.
So they go over
there and scratch it.
And then this is my
bait stick right here.
This is the trigger
of the whole trap.
I got a big old cricket.
I'm gonna go out of
my way to put as much
guinea delicious-y goodness
on this thing as I can.
I want him to be like, "Ha!
Look at what I just found."
And then, quick try to eat
it before his buddies notice.
And his greed
will be his downfall.
He's gonna peck at this...
and then, boom,
you get a guinea.
All right, that's one trap done.
On to trap number two.
Our firewood supply
is getting kind of low.
That sounds good.
Yeah, I like the sound of that.
Where we just walked
through, it looked like there was
-tons of wood.
-Yeah, I've seen that.
Out here, when you're
surviving, you have to have
a firewood inside
your shelter at all times,
especially at night,
because whether it's rain
coming in or it's big
predators coming close,
if we hear our trip line go off,
then we can build
up our fire a little bit,
get a little more
smoke in the air,
just to further
protect ourselves.
All right, that's a pile there.
Give us a chance
to get that fire going.
Flare up a little.
'Cause these are gonna
start coming and prowling,
'cause we've got meat
and guts on each side
of our shelter.
I do.
I do not get tired of it.
-Oh, my God.
-The camera... hell!
Thank you!
That's a black
mamba, there, too.
-Is it?
-Yep.
Holy crap.
Don't move, don't move.
Oh, my God.
Hell!
Oh, man, that's scary as.
Yep.
Yeah.
Right there.
Oh.
That's a black mamba.
Holy crap.
Where did he come from?
I have no idea.
Yeah.
Yeah, it crawled
right underneath there.
And after that, I have no idea.
Oh, man! Thank you
for spotting it, buddy.
, that was a bit of a scare.
Yeah, it is a lot of a scare.
And it's gonna get
pitch black soon.
Oh, man!
We need to ash that
ever-loving hell out of this.
Just here or throw
them under there?
As cold blooded reptiles,
snakes seek shade
from extreme heat in order
to cool their body temperature,
so spreading warm
ash can help deter them.
You might have saved
my life right there.
No joke, you might
have saved my life.
It was a really close call.
Yeah, it's a black mamba.
He bites you and you're
dead, and he was in our shelter.
We don't know how far he
went, but we threw burning ash
in there and coals,
and then ashed the
doorway really good.
He won't come back, hopefully.
Just almost turned deadly.
I don't know
about sleep tonight.
I'm on the edge right now, man.
Yeah, I don't feel
good over here at all.
How many things are
gonna happen to us?
The line comes through
camp, and then I have a damn
black mamba at the
foot from my head.
Very, very scary.
I was feeling any weaker
or anything like that,
just a little mentally
bad. I'd be gone.
Yeah, I got some
praying to do tonight.
That was scary.
Not worth it.
Get me the out of here.
Ugh, goddamn, man.
I'm tired.
Right now, I'm
back to being weak.
Not just weak, but like worried,
so I built a fishing line
and that's what I hope
is gonna pay off, so that...
I don't have to keep
going days without eating.
And we're gonna take a scorpion.
There we go.
Now we've got a baited hook.
The line's super
heavy, it's wire.
So I'm gonna try
and use a Y stick here
to, uh, prop it up in the water.
Well, I set the line,
scorpion's on there.
We'll leave this
in here overnight,
see if the scorpion gets eaten.
You may get lucky, you
may get a starving catfish
in hopes of a scorpion meal.
So we'll see what happens.
I think I see a
bunch of frogs here.
Tons of frogs.
They're poisonous, but maybe
I can use them as bait too.
Let's see how quick they are.
Got a little
poisonous white frog.
I can bait the catfish trap,
and then hopefully that'll be
more enticing than
just that old bone.
They need something
bit new on the menu.
Nothing, nothing, nothing, OK.
All right.
So we got a dangly-gutted frog.
That looks awesome.
And we'll see if
that gets us a yield.
I have really high hopes
for that trap now yielding
with that frog, and if I
come check in the morning,
and it has fish in
it, and guess what?
I'm putting another
frog in there.
You know, it's like, if
that's gonna yield me more
than this makeshift
fishing line,
that would be an amazing score.
Starting to get
a little blackout.
Jesus, it's getting
dangerous to stand up.
Kept getting really lightheaded,
almost to the point where I...
just lo... losing
track of where I'm at,
what I'm doing.
I'm afraid that I don't
have the guts to...
ride this out this far.
Yeah.
Last night, sleep
was a little rough.
I had thoughts about
that black mamba all night.
They talk about getting rattled.
Yeah, that thing bites you,
and you're... you're dead.
When something
like that happens,
you have a moment
of reflection and you go,
"What in the hell
am I doing here?
I might not ever
see my family again."
Yeah.
Yeah, I got hit with being
very tired for some reason.
-Your body needs it.
-I guess so.
I guess so.
Are you OK?
Um, I don't know.
Let's go check some bird snares.
Now, let's see.
This one is still set
and the bait is still there.
I just don't think
they've been by it
or just haven't seen it yet.
OK, so the second
one is right up here.
Let's go see if we
still got bait in this one.
No, nothing, still set.
Nothing.
You know, our traps,
we got them out there.
It's just a matter of time.
So I'm gonna explore
around a little bit
and maybe try to
find something to eat.
It is very important to
keep exploring your area,
'cause that's how
you find things.
Like, everything's
moving out here.
This is a fluid environment,
you know, including the plants.
The plants are moving,
they're moving up.
But, uh...
this looks like a
little scorpion hole.
Let's see if anybody's home.
Something's grabbing this, see?
There's a scorpion in this hole.
Yeah. Look at the
pinch marks on it.
I wanna dig it out.
I mean, obviously,
the thing is dangerous,
but I still gotta catch it.
Even small protein
sources that are fresh
are worth its weight in gold.
This is gonna take a second
'cause I don't want him
to go too deep.
There are over 130
different species of scorpion
in South Africa.
To escape extreme
heat and avoid predators,
many create underground burrows,
digging anywhere from a
few inches to three feet deep.
If disturbed, their
neurotoxic venom
can cause intense
pain, muscle paralysis,
and potential
respiratory failure.
Oh, and I see it.
Yeah, OK, here he is. I got 'em.
Let's get him out now.
Ooh, he is not happy.
Oh, there he is.
OK.
So... And here's how
you deal with these guys.
Like this.
He's not happy.
Now, this won't kill you,
but you're not gonna enjoy
the sting from it.
I've been stung by
several scorpions
in the United States and, uh...
it could hurt for
anywhere from 30 minutes
to three days.
So now that I know I can do this
and they're not that deep,
I could probably dig
out 30 of these guys
and just like eat them
like popcorn chicken.
It's crucial that we
find another source
of protein out here.
And every little bit adds
up when you're waiting
on a big kill.
So now it's time
to go get my team
and get after these guys.
Oh, more firewood. Good.
-It got really cold last night.
-Yeah, it did.
We're halfway
through this challenge.
And today is
definitely hunting day.
So, Teal, she's
determined, I like it.
I hope it pays off
because she hasn't had
that perfect opportunity yet.
And... but I'm sure
when it comes,
she gonna make the most of it.
Oh, yes.
I think it might be
a juvenile duiker,
heading straight
up to the field,
right where the blind is.
Hey Teal, I can see
something about three quarters
of the way up to the
farmhouse up there.
It looks like a little
duiker or something,
but it's moving around
slow, do you wanna go?
Do you wanna take the bow
and arrow up there and see...
see if you can get it?
Duiker's tasty.
Yeah, let me check it out.
Aim small, miss small.
Getting within, you know,
20 yards of an animal
and feeling confident
on a shot is, you know,
makes me a little nervous.
But when the
opportunity presents itself,
just take the shot,
because what's the worst
thing that could happen?
Oh, I see him! Yes,
yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
I see him. I see him.
I'm looking at this
duiker, and it's sitting there
staring at me.
Maybe this thing is
sick or heat exhausted.
It seems a little disoriented.
But you don't get
many shots out here,
and you rarely get one
that's as sure as this.
He's such a small target.
I don't wanna get too close.
'cause I don't
wanna startle him.
He's such a small target.
I don't wanna get too close
'cause I don't
wanna startle him.
Definitely got him.
Oh, he's not feeling good.
Oh, God.
Thank you, sweet thing.
He's not going anywhere.
Just rest.
Just close your
eyes and rest, it's OK.
I saw you shooting
at something, Teal.
How'd it go?
Yeah, I got him in the chest.
-You good?
-Yeah, I'm OK.
I'm proud of you for
getting that shot on target.
A little bit of that practice,
and look how it's paid off.
I thought he was
going to get away.
Just wait here, Teal.
Let me check it real quick.
Yep.
It's obviously dead.
-You good, kid?
-Yeah, I'm fine.
Just one of those
things about survival is,
you know, this is part
of what we do, and...
part of how it all
works, it sucks.
Like, I feel as bad
as anyone else.
I'm not naive, I know
where my food comes from.
-Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
-I just don't like this part.
Yeah, yeah, I get it.
I get it.
It's unfortunate, but... Yeah.
We've got a little
bit more food,
which is a positive spin on it.
We just need to get past this.
Get past this little
bit, you know?
Yeah.
I'll carry it down
here, and we'll...
we'll field dress it down there.
Under the tree again.
It'll be a lot easier this time.
We're gonna get this meat ready.
We're not gonna
waste one bit of this.
We've got a process
we're gonna follow.
Gonna get the guts out,
we're gonna save all this meat,
cook some up, eat
some, and jerky some.
I was able to shoot the duiker,
but I don't feel so great.
It's just hard to do
it, and even aiming
and taking the shot, I feel
like my brain is just like, "miss."
We don't have a
choice, we have still
more than two weeks to
go, and we have to eat,
but it's still really hard.
Watching Teal get
emotional, it's something
I've experienced before.
It's something I
definitely understand.
You're taking
something's life, but...
in an apocalyptic
environment, this is a real thing
that we need to
do as survivalists.
So you have to pay
respect as much as you can,
doing the right thing
about the animal
once it's been
harvested by just getting
as much of that resource
out of the animal's
body as possible.
It's just hard.
Should we start
looking for scorpions?
Yeah.
-Oh, yeah, got one.
-Oh, you have?
Yeah, see?
Oh, yeah, he's in there.
Oh, yeah.
We need food, we need protein.
So we got a bunch of scorpions.
We're gonna dig up for a
little scorpion popcorn party.
I think that might
be him right there.
-Got him.
-Is he a big one?
Well, it's not real big.
Wee!
Cut the stinger off.
-Boom.
-Perfect.
-Amazing!
-Scorpion!
-Oh, wow.
-Scorpion.
-One down.
-Oh!
Is there any meat on a scorpion?
Yeah, probably eight
grams of protein in one.
-Really?
-Scorpions actually
have more protein per weight
than any mammal, any bird,
any snake, or
reptile or amphibia.
So we're looking for at least...
We're looking for
nine, aren't we?
Ooh, are we going that hard?
Yeah, we have three apiece.
All right, goodness, OK.
We can feast.
So even though they're
not the most appetizing,
as far as nutritional
value, it's top notch.
At this point, I'm excited
about eating anything at all.
Ooh, without
taking the stinger off.
Use the other end, and
you'll feel it and bite it.
It's like you're
scorpion fishing.
-There's one in here.
-Yeah?
Yeah.
All right.
Can't let all you boys
have all the fun, you know?
-There she is.
-It's crazy.
Scorpion kebab,
all right, six to go.
Woo-hoo!
Oh, mama, I'm so sorry.
After I got the kill, I
felt really conflicted.
I felt kind of like...
accomplished, but
also kind of sad.
It's difficult, but being able
to provide a meal to my team
is an act of care
and it's important,
and I wanna be here for it
because I want to be able to be
that provider as well.
That's good.
We're gonna have some
red meat in our bellies,
which is awesome.
Teal getting a duiker was
emotionally draining on her,
but if Teal hadn't found
this thing when she did,
it wouldn't have taken...
wouldn't have taken many minutes
before something
else was eating it.
So, you know,
unfortunately, this one
lost its life, but you know,
we're gonna be able to get a lot
out of this thing,
so it's a godsend.
Got the heart right
there, that's gonna be
a good little bit.
We gotta eat the
back straps, period.
100%, we're eating
the back strap,
eating the heart,
eating the kidneys.
And then we'll just strip
the strips of meat away
from the legs and
string them up.
And we'll smoke 'em.
It's got to take this one
last leg off and we're done.
We're definitely in a
place where, if we had to,
we could go all the way
to 35 with just the meat
that we have right now.
It's a safety net we can
fall back on if we have to.
Gonna get the smoker cracking.
The last time we used
the smoker in the rain,
it was hard keeping
the coals alive
and keeping the temperature up.
We might have a bit of a
better grasp on it this time,
just in relation to
controlling the temperature.
Here we go.
Nice, fresh red meat.
We should be able to turn
a lot of this into the jerky
before the sun goes down.
And we're gonna
eat some as well,
which is gonna be great.
It's gonna get a
nice little cook on.
All right, check my fish traps.
See if there's anything in them.
Just so depleted right now.
It's day 18 of the challenge.
Pretty hungry, I can't
even remember the last time
I had catfish.
The two step forward,
one step back of surviving
this apocalyptic
landscape is taking a toll.
So I'm hoping the scorpion
at least got chewed up.
See if scorpion
is an effective bait.
Yeah, nothing really doing here.
Damn it. That's a bummer.
So Scorpion was eaten.
All right, just
spit out the hook.
So they will take
the scorpion bait.
All right.
But now the big
one, I'm really hoping
this yields, 'cause...
we have fresh
bait, but you know,
they like stinky
rotten stuff, so...
It could just end up taking
a few days for this frog
to get real gross.
And then they will
be like, "Yes, please."
And they'll line
up to come in here.
Come on, baby.
Nothing says team bonding
like a family dinner of
scorpion shish kebab.
Arachnids on a stick.
You really wanna
hear that crackle pop.
That's usually when their guts
kind of explode inside of them.
That's when you know
that their innards are boiling.
Sounds super appetizing.
We found about nine scorpions.
This one isn't physically
huge, but it is mentally huge.
-We got our scorps.
-Cheers!
-Team building!
-Team Alpha.
On the tongue.
Mmm.
-Oh, it's rough.
-Yeah.
That one had dirt in it.
-Pretty sure that's sand.
-It's all crunch.
It's just exoskeleton and
dirt and Africa in your mouth.
Yeah, that was weird.
There we go!
We got a terrapin
stuck in there.
Absolutely incredible.
No doubt.
All I know is I have
a source of protein,
and that makes me feel good.
It's a good amount of meat.
In these apocalyptic
times, you're a meal.
And I'm super stoked about it.
I think this is
an old fan cover.
I found this in the
ruins the other day.
All right, now
we're cooking them.
All right.
I feel proud.
I feel proud about
my trap working.
So good to be getting a
meal that actually makes me
feel stronger, knowing
that my body's gonna get
a little bit of nourishment.
I haven't eaten
anything in probably
more than a week now.
I needed some
food, I was starting...
starting to waste
away, so I know it's...
only about, you know,
big in my hand, but...
it's a meal.
Wow.
That's pleasant.
That's really good, actually.
A terrapin this size will yield
about five ounces of meat
and provide the same
amount of protein
as a beef burger patty.
That is good for me.
You know, out here,
little things like this
are coping boosters, you know,
and I feel I need it today.
You know, I need that
confidence right now,
going forward,
with trying to hunt
and acquire a bigger meal.
You know, that's my
number one goal right now.
And if I get that, then
I'm gonna be able
to ride through this challenge.
Be ready to rock and roll.
It's pretty much done.
-Looks lovely.
-It does, doesn't it?
There you go.
-Cheers.
Just juicy.
Mm.
It's really tender.
It's absolutely mouth watering,
and the mouthfeel is chewy
but not tough, and
juicy, and just delicious.
It's so good.
To be standing here,
eating, not just eating,
-but eating fresh.
-It's really nice.
And yeah, I think all
the hard work we put in
eventually turned
our luck, you know?
Yep.
Into something you harvested.
More than halfway
through the challenge,
and I must admit, we've made
a pretty darn good
living for ourselves.
We have a great shelter,
a massive amount of food,
and we're feeling
like we're pros.
I can't believe how
well we're thriving.
We're so set up now.
Still good.
All the work is done.
That duiker's processed.
Uh, the meat is hanging
up inside the smoker.
Flames at the bottom,
smoke coming up.
And we have...
where is that sun at?
One and a half
hours before the sun
touches the horizon.
So, probably, two
hours of work here.
We can get this probably
to a place in two hours
where we can just
take it and hang it inside.
Then I don't have to
worry about it overnight,
which would be perfect.
So we've got all this
meat down near the boma.
They could invite
scavengers in overnight.
So it's just about
keeping that stuff away
from the predators in the area.
-Cheers.
-Cheers!
The wind outside is kicking.
So I started a little
comfort fire here.
Also, we've got
full bellies right now.
So full to the top,
lots of red meat in us,
lots of energy, lots
of forward momentum.
Everything's going well.
Including our meat chandelier.
Good job today, Teal.
Very proud of you.
Great day.
-That's you, right?
-Hmm?
-Is that you moving?
-No, what was it?
What the is that?
Is that a lion?
OK, now I'm freaking out.
There are so many
noises tonight.
And I just heard
a really big one.
It sounded like a long brush
up against the shelter, like fur.
I swear I even heard growling.
It's freaking me out.
-Oh, my God!
-Jesus Christ!